[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is felina for
software engineering radio today with me
on the show is jordan adler he has been
a professional software developer since
2003 he is currently engineering
director for developer engineering at
onesignal previously he was api
platform engineer at pinterest and
developer advocate at google welcome to
the show jordan today's topic is code
generation so let's start with a
definition what for you is code
generation
that's a great question so code
generation is any tech it's a technique
that you can use in software engineering
where essentially your software is
producing code as an output rather than
some kind of expected it's some other
kind of expected user behavior
so for example a common code generation
technique would be transpilation
wherein unlike a compiler which compiles
programming code into machine code a
transpiler compiles
or translates
programming code from one language to
another and so a common one of these
would be type check right so typescript
converts you know into javascript and
conducts some kind of type checks along
the way
that would be an example of
transpilation which is a type of
cogeneration technique
yeah that's immediately an interesting
question an international example
because that leads to the question like
why are we generating source code why
are we not just typing source code right
so what is the benefit of generating
javascript from typescript or in other
contexts generating certain pieces of
software
if we can also type that right i get it
for assembler no one wants to type bit
code or assembler but why javascript is
fine why are we generating this
yeah there are lots of different reasons
to do that you know typically the the
answer is productivity of one reason or
another right so if you are trying to
write a piece of software and there's a
lot of duplicate code in that piece of
software perhaps it's duplicated because
you are
one of five different teams each trying
to build a system and they all interact
with each other and maybe they use
different languages but they all have
the same kind of interface or the same
specified method of kind of interacting
with each other then you might want to
procedurally generate kind of that
interface code so that when you actually
change the way that servers communicate
with each other you only have to change
them in one place instead of five places
so that that's a common reason another
common reason could be to
like i mentioned with the typescript
javascript perhaps you're conducting
some kind of checks and in the process
producing
uh code that is consumable by some other
tool another example might be you know
lots of folks have kubernetes yaml right
that becomes unwieldy repetitive after a
while and so there are tools out there
that can actually produce kubernetes for
you based off of templating and so that
process effectively generates code
declarative code that is the kind of
kubernetes consumes
and so there's lots of different kinds
of reasons that people might want to do
this but typically they boil down
productivity you have some kind of
machine that or some kind of system that
expects either kind of a computer system
or a system of people that expects kind
of code to come in at one way and
transpilation can kind of enable you to
fit that standard or it's technique you
can use to enable you to fit that
requirement while reducing the cost of
actually
yes generally it's quicker and it might
also be less error prone because you can
do some checking before you actually
generate the code so you know you're
generating correct codes in for a
definition of correct
absolutely you can test for correctness
you can duplicate code so you can kind
of produce multiple different versions
of the same input right so the process
of doing that as opposed to having
someone write it out right it's a lot
quicker
and less airplane absolutely
yeah that makes sense so you already
sort of hinted at some concrete examples
but can you give a certain example of a
situation in which you use a coach
generating tool
to solve a specific problem
yeah so one one example
would be we have this tool called
cli tool that we've built for the
prototype and what it does is at one
signal what it does is it creates a it
injects kind of the code into an
application
to add an sdk into kind of a mobile
application so you have a code base it's
an android app or an ios app for example
you can run this tool it'll scan the
software or the the the programming code
for that application and inject conduct
the right changes to actually inject the
required changes to the code to be able
to include the sdk so this is a kind of
code transforming process technique code
transformation where you take
one piece of code you output another
piece of code but you've modified the
code in some way not unlike
transpilation but the difference here is
we're not converting from one language
to another we're just kind of keeping it
in the same language maybe we're
semantically changing the behavior of
the application
yeah so we're like enriching an existing
code base with some features and later
in the episode we want to dive into code
transformation specifically as
like a separate process from code
generation
i'm also wondering like are there empty
patterns are there situations in which
you would say that code generation might
not be the right solution
yeah i mean oftentimes it adds quite a
bit of complexity particularly in your
build tool chain so if you if you have a
situation where you think you're you
know you might be able to save developer
time
by
co-generating some piece of the code
base before kind of building and
producing it now that that kind of adds
on to your build process
so that can add time to each build that
you do both in in terms of like when the
software is actually shipped but also in
terms of development right so you have
to kind of have a local development loop
you have to build you have to test you
iterate you know if you have kind of
code generation in the mix during that
kind of tight developer loop it'll end
up taking longer and so
you know oftentimes the trade-off here
is yes i'm spending a lot less time
writing code but i'm spending you know a
lot more time waiting for code to be
generated that is a trade-off that you
have to make potentially and the
productivity gains will have to outweigh
the cost of both establishing the code
generation pattern which is complicated
certainly and rife with issues but also
in in terms of the cost of kind of using
it and maintaining it which includes
quite a bit of complexity in the built
in and time cost in the execution of
that chain
yeah that makes sense i know we want to
talk about this the whole build process
of code generation also deeper in there
in the episodes but one question maybe
that sounds a little bit abstract still
for people that have never used code
generation tools it's like what is a
code generation tool look like
do i write code to generate code or is
this a visual tool where i sort of click
the interfaces together and then it
generates code from a from a visual
model from something like uml
what does code generation look like
practically
that's a great question you know i think
in in practice all of those are kind of
common uis for dealing with cogeneration
there are tools that you can use kind of
in a one-off basis visual tools for
example to build out let's say sql
specification like a set of sql
statements to create tables you know
there are lots of tools out there table
table designing tools that produce as an
output some kind of you know sql
statement that can be consumed by a
series of sql statements that can be
consumed by a database
that is a case certainly another common
one perhaps the most common one again
going back to the ideals case if you
have something like swagger which is an
api specification
now called open api specification
previously called swagger you know you
can have in yaml or json a definition of
a rest api
and run a cli tool that procedurally
generates from that specification
client libraries or perhaps servers you
know or pieces of server code that is
then consumed by a java application that
fills out stubs of those you know of
that interface right so it can vary in
terms of interface it can be cli based
it can be gui based it can be something
you use once as part of your development
process and never use again it could be
something that you use every single time
you build and it could be something you
use manually when you need to pull
something in from upstream it's a
technique that can be used in many
different ways for sure
nice so that gives us a lot of ways to
apply code generation in projects now we
have generated code so the code has been
generated with one of the variety of the
tools that you just described so that
now what do i manually read this code is
there some sort of verification or do i
verify the generation what do you do in
that case like do you ever look at the
generated code is it ever necessary to
inspect that or is it sort of correct by
construction
oh absolutely and you know you can
establish a pattern by which you can
kind of procedurally generate code and
then have that be tested in a way that
you know enables you to build confidence
that it's an error free for example
when i was at pinterest we were using
code transformation to convert our code
base from python 2 to python 3. that was
part of the migration that we were doing
at that time
and that process you know as we were
kind of converting bits and pieces of
the code from python to python three
well we could
you know deploy a piece you know to
convert a small chunk of it deploy it to
a portion of our overall fleet
let's say two percent and then if two
percent of our fleet is running this new
version with these new modifications and
it's getting all the same you know api
requests and returning all the same
outputs and not having any new errors
not producing any new issues we can
probably say that it's safely kind of
consistent between the two versions we
deploy it so in cases where you have
kind of a deploy process where you may
be canary-like or have some other
processes statistically eliminating kind
of risk and you can move forward
carefully then automating the process of
deploying code generations is not
unreasonable
yeah so i wanted to say like this is a
situation in which you already have
running code you have a baseline right
you know what it's supposed to do and
you can
migrate parts of it but this is of
course not always the case so i was
wondering if you also have examples of
experience with sort of freshly
generating code where you do not have a
baseline to test again
oh absolutely and in most cases you
really should manually inspect the code
so even when we were working on
pinterest on this tool on this sorry
this project to convert from python to
python 3 we were
routinely manually inspecting the
changes that were coming through and
honestly like some of the code
transformation we had they were very
they were not error-prone at all right
they were fairly straightforward convert
this function you know add parentheses
after print right so print is no longer
statement now it's a function that's a
pretty straightforward
thing to change
until you start throwing in complexities
like well what if we have our own
function called print that we shadowed
right so we have kind of you know monkey
patched our own print function or what
if we have some kind of special label in
our code called printed you know that
we've modified some way so it's not
keyword or what if we have
you know function calls that look like
print and perhaps the regex that we use
to convert the code or whatever
technique that we use to actually
implement the code transformation was a
little overzealous and so we have error
and so we'd often kind of run through
and manually review all the changes as
part of our pr process that would
actually happen
however if you were to run code
generation in automated fashion
for example we have at one signal api
client libraries that i mentioned again
that we we procedurally generate from
open api specification files
and so the output of that can change
from version aversion as we pull in you
know changes from our upstream open api
generator open source repository
um we pull them in manually we re-run
the code generation and then we review
the changes that occur kind of before
landing them because you you can't say
for certain what the changes will be so
that is more of a manual kind of review
process than something like the kind of
the canary based um
or even kind of the
the pr inspection which is much more
kind of scrolling through thousands and
thousands of changes and looking for
outliers as opposed to kind of really
deeply inspecting every single line
that's changed trying to understand it
and understanding
yeah that makes sense and i guess
there's also a difference between if you
are the person that is authoring the go
generation tooling or if you're simply
using something that has been
extensively tested and probably you can
rely a little bit more on the fact that
the generation will be correct because
it has already been tested by many other
people
that's a really great point and i think
you've hit on something interesting
about code generation which is that it
often involves you know collaboration
between people it's a technique that is
pulled out when two teams or two groups
or two pieces of software have to
interact with each other or two or more
really
and so having that kind of consideration
of okay where is this code coming from
who wrote the code generator and
understanding that is as much of a
process of understanding how to
integrate deploy this technique in your
code base as anything else
so let's talk about practicalities yeah
you already mentioned that this code
generation will then be part of your
build process which might be time
consuming but also you get some
interesting questions like what do i do
with the generated source code do i
check this in to version control or is
this typically something that you would
put in a get ignore because well if you
need it you can just generate it again i
can again imagine that for reasons of
traceability maybe you also want to ship
the generated code so you are sure that
everyone looks at the same version of it
what are your best practices there
yeah i mean i think it is going to vary
i don't think there are kind of standard
approaches again i it's an unfortunate
answer i think you know when it comes to
code generation code transformation and
really kind of more broadly you know
compilation and kind of the
consideration of kind of managing code
there are lots of different ways to to
kind of treat code as data and lots of
different patterns of kind of using that
i have seen cases where
people have
kind of generated code and then for
example in java right and then created
you know modified the exact same file to
change out the stub you know functions
actually implement them
and then on kind of updates to the
api where you can kind of then
procedurally generate
the changes to the server function then
you can just kind of get a patch file
run that against your file and then
manually edit it right so that that can
work you can have kind of good mixed
code in in the same files if you're
going to be manually editing and
manually reviewing it
if you're going to be automating it i
probably would not um kind of have them
be in the same files i probably would
also you know whether or not you checked
it in depends on whether you know the
generated code is more of an
intermediary object or more of a kind of
desired output of some kind and so that
will depend right so example the api
client libraries the generated code you
know is the product right and so for us
having that be checked into version
control
actually makes sense
not in the repository that contains all
the code that generates it so we have a
code that what one repo where all the
code is generated for the client
libraries and then you know let's say 10
other repos for each of the client
libraries one for each of the other
client libraries java go c sharp rust
and so on
and so the reality is that you will need
to kind of use whatever approach makes
sense
my only cautionary statement here and
kind of the good rule of rule of thumb
here is
you know when you're working with with a
language that's typed you want to take
advantage of that typing
and if you produce if you're using code
generation in a way that basically
creates an intermediary layer between
the procedurally generated types and
the types that you're actually using in
your handwritten code in other words if
your handwritten code and your generated
code have kind of two totally different
type graphs and they are not connected
at all then your type checker is not
really doing its job
and and that's that's a problem so you
do have to be conscious of that but
other than that i would say that there's
no kind of hard and fast rule it really
depends on the situation
yeah i think i can add an example there
from a project that i work on myself
because sometimes it's also about like
what tooling do you expect people to
have so we have a backhand that's in
python and most of our open source
developers actually work on the python
site and then we have a little front end
that's written in typescript that we
then transpile to javascript so we do
check in the generated javascript
because just because we think that it's
a hassle for the python developers to
have to generate the javascript
themselves they might not have npm it
might just not be ready for that type of
tooling so it's like a courtesy to
people we're like oh here's the
generated code if you're if you're not
changing anything in the front end you
don't need to compile or transfile the
code so sometimes it's also about do you
require the users or the contributors in
your project to also install all the
code generation tooling which might
sometimes be also
complex to deal with so that's maybe
also a consideration that you can have
that not only who will or who needs to
generate the code but also who will sort
of feel like installing all the tools
that make the code generation happen
that's a really interesting point and i
kind of actually interestingly enough is
an illustrative of the difference
between
kind of commercial applications
of this technique and kind of open
source or academia where you want
volunteers you want you want people to
join and so you want to kind of minimize
the cost the threshold effort to
contribute code and that's not true
necessarily in a commercial setting
where i've been doing most of my
practitioner work right in a corporate
environment where i can say well you
know
you just have to do what i say yes
exactly install this thing or i i you
know added it to the device management
so you don't even realize it but you
already have java compiler so it's
obviously
yeah because sometimes this can really
be a big blocker like i was looking into
another code generation tool and then
it's like yeah you have to install
eclipse and this version of java i am
never used java and then there's sort of
a need for open source work it is a
threshold like well if it requires me to
install java then i don't feel like
doing this maybe it's not worth it so
that the tooling angle and it's very
right that you point this out is very
different in open source projects where
indeed we want to make it as easy for
you as possible we don't want to force
python developers to install tooling
that are like what is this
yeah that's a great point there there
are lots of kind of toolkits out there
for you know open source toolkits for
generating or building code generation
tooling
one of them is called yellow code which
is written in javascript for typescript
writer and that one is one that we ended
up using for a lot of our web sdk so we
kind of procedurally generate blue code
that sits on top of our web sdks
specific to react review
or angular and so you know we're able to
produce those kind of procedurally
generate higher level sdks for these
frameworks on top of our web sdk
but we didn't want to do that using the
same kind of java based tooling that we
use for our back end stuff right and so
yellow code is this really nice kind of
typescript tool chain
big system for building these things i
have to imagine that some extent exists
in part because of what you were saying
right like you know there's a lot of
these things existed beforehand but none
of them kind of in the same
tool
with the same consistent yeah exactly or
compiler yeah we will definitely add a
link in the show notes to that jelly
code tool
then i was also wondering what about
documentation right so if i'm generating
code
where does my documentation live do i
generate documentation that's in the
generated code for when people inspect
the generated code or is that
documentation typically placed wherever
i'm writing the specifications for the
generation whether that is in a
different programming language or in a
visual tool or is this something that
lives in a markdown file where it just
says this is how you generate the code
and this is what happens are there any
best practices there
yeah i mean i i think that the best
practices when it comes to documentation
is
yes
all of them you know i think it'll
depend so
to give you an example we'll we'll often
proceed to really generate like i said
api client libraries right and that
includes our api reference in it so we
have kind of you know a python
classes that are stuffed out that
include doc strings or documentation and
an inline as python developers expect
them
and that comes from our yaml file the
open aps
open api specification kind of gamma
file that says okay this uh if you call
a put on this path on our server that is
actually this function and here's what
does and here the parameters and so on
and so that kind of yaml file is
consumed procedurally generates and
actually creates the client libraries
and so we have kind of one place where
we kind of update those api reference
documentation and can then propagate
that downstream to 10 different client
libraries very easily so that's one
place where documentation exists and and
so that's kind of that in-line
you know documentation in kind of the
resultant client libraries
we can also procedurally generate just
an api reference itself right so kind of
a markdown you know think of it as
instead of producing a typescript output
of this kind of api specification we're
producing a markdown output and open api
generator the open source project
includes kind of an output so you can
procedurally generate markdown
documentation or other kinds of
documentation actually to be able to to
host and serve alongside the client
library so that's kind of another
form of documentation
yet again we also have the documentation
in the open api generator project itself
which explains how to use it right so
that that's kind of one piece but in our
own kind of repo where we host all the
code that actually executes as part of
our tool chain opening channel and
includes all of our patches to the
downstream libraries
that repository also includes
instructions for people who are working
on our client libraries on how to
specifically use it for us right which
includes by the way you know how to
patch the breed be for the resulting
client libraries to have kind of
manually crafted readings because the
procedurally generated client libraries
from the upstream templates are not
always kind of super useful immediately
so there's documentation api reference
that's being kind of inserted into the
code that's being resolved in as well as
produced as an additional target that we
can serve alongside our client libraries
as well as the documentation that exists
for the developers using
or working on our system and not the
ones that are consuming the code
produced by the system
yes yeah so so indeed there are these
different forms of documentation that's
probably a good idea to have it anywhere
and if you have so specification about
what you're going to generate you know
you might as well generate that
specification
cool so let's go from code generation
more towards code transformation we have
already talked about this a little bit
but
what exactly is code transformation now
we have a process in which the input is
code and the output is also code but
then there's also code defining the
transformation so what does code
transformation look like for you
so if you think about kinetic code
generation code transformation as both
things that output code right
compilation also outputs code right so
compilation takes in programming code
outputs machine code transpilation takes
in programming code outputs programming
code maybe in a different language
code generation takes in
something semantically and outputs code
right it doesn't have to be code it can
be some kind of configuration object or
something like that
code transformation however takes in
code and outputs more or less the exact
same code but having been modified and
so code transformers sometimes called
code modifiers
code modifiers they can take a variety
of different shapes in terms of how
they're implemented but really what they
try to do is produce something that's
basically the same same language but
with some modification in the code
itself either semantically in the case
of say
you know a code transformer that's
trying to change the behavior of a
function
you know and maybe you have to change
everywhere it's called as a result right
if you have a very large code base you
might not want to do that manually you
might write a little code transformer to
update you know the function and
everywhere it's called to change the
parameters that are being passed around
you know so that's a that is a you know
kind of one consideration
like how code transformation is
different than kind of other techniques
yeah so your example made me think of a
refactoring right so adding a parameter
or changing the order of parameters this
is something i can do in the ide i right
click a function in most ids and then i
can reorder the parameters so
that is
a refactoring but also a code
transformation like like is it
refactoring an example of
a code transformation or is it not
because it's not really done with a code
generation tool
i think refactoring is a common
goal or common common cause or use of
code transformation you talk about find
or replace an ide so if you pull up like
you know eclipse or something you go
find or place that is a code
transformation right you found code
you've replaced it a switch statement in
vim
that's a code transformer right
right so then we've identified like one
tool to do code transformation with the
ide but i guess there's also other tools
in which we write codes to to script the
transformation or to visually manipulate
the transformation what are tools that
you typically use for code
transformation
that's right so if you take code and
you're trying to transform it the code
the tools that you will use will depend
on the language itself so i talked a bit
about yellow code before yellow code is
kind of a tool kit for for parsing you
know so it's a toolkit for making code
transformers and so it has
elements of it that enable you to parse
languages and and represent
programming code in a given language say
typescript as a data object of some kind
and and really like if you think about
okay what is a code generator what is a
code transformer of some kind well it
starts by it's really a two-step process
right step one
get code into data step two get you know
i guess three steps if you're
transforming it right mudge that data
somehow and step three would be kind of
producing or outputting that data back
as code again
and there's lots of different ways that
you can do that and lots of tools you
can do that with you can roll your own
certainly or you can use compiler tool
chains that often have that first step
covered and that third step which is
convert code to data and data back in
the code
and then what you are manipulating in
between is the data representation which
will often be a parse tree i guess
so it can be a parse stream so now we're
getting kind of deeper into kind of
parsing and for folks who have taken
compiler classes you might remember some
of these these things but you can use an
abstract syntax tree um which which kind
of includes enough of the information
for you to be able to take
you know a representation of programming
code and turn it back into source code
because remember not not all
representations of programming code can
be turned back into source code once
you've stripped out white space and
comments and so on you can't immediately
turn it back and so a lot of compilers
will have kind of actual multiple steps
we'll go abstract syntax tree and then
we'll trim that down to a concrete
syntax tray then they'll transform that
and into light code of some kind that
actually gets piped into say the jvm or
python's virtual machine
but in our case we're going to go part
of the way so for python as an example
we can actually use python's ast
module the thing that python itself uses
to represent python programs as code and
pipe code you know read code from text
put it into there and then once it's in
that ast kind of class then we can
modify it as we like
but there are other ways too
for example you don't have to use kind
of a complex compiler tool chain you can
just use regex or
even kind of look for strings and kind
of manipulate strings really any
any way that you can kind of manage
string or text as strings you can use
for code too but
the less
context aware that you your
implementation is the more risky it is
in terms of the error-proneness of the
output and the less kind of you know
because you have to imagine if you're
going to be running this code
transformer on multiple different kinds
of code bases you know not all code
bases are created equal if you test on a
million lines of code but a particular
pattern was never seen there's some bug
in your your kind of transformer that
you just don't know about
and you won't be encountered until
someone else picks it up and uses it and
they may not be well equipped and so you
have to think about that as you're
designing your transformer but certainly
like simplest possible implementation
could be you know a bash
script that is basically a one-liner
call to you know uh find a replacement
set or vim or something like that yeah
and of course it can be easy but also
more air prone if you are
transforming python 2 to python 3 then
you just want to add brackets around
every print you could do that with a
little bit of string magic but then
maybe you're not really sure that every
print you encountered is actually really
the print that you want to transform
so let's talk a little bit more about
this case study because you have worked
on this python 2 to python 3
transformation project and i would love
to hear more about like did you do
everything automatically or were there
some edge cases that had to be
transformed manually and what was your
approach can you just take us through
that project how you approached it
absolutely and so i talked a bit about
this project at pycon a few years ago
let's say around 2017 you should be able
to find it online if you'd like so we'll
add a link to the show notes
excellent pinterest python 2 to python 3
migration and we used a tool called
python future which is produced by an
outfit called python charmers out of
australia that i've been collaborating
with and python future
includes a number of things kind of
related or tools that are useful for
this endeavor of going from a python 2
to python 3 kind of system
the first is a set of code transformers
code modifiers that
kind of take python 2 code and convert
it into python 2 code
but in a way that is more
aligned with or more gradually
incrementally more you know consumable
pie python right so there is a
a set of things that are syntactically
different between python 2 and python 3
as an example print move from a
statement to a function so you have to
put parentheses around it now right so
it's no longer a special case function
call
so that that can be done with a code
transformer and python actually included
a function called underscore underscore
future underscore underscore
which in the python world would call
dunder future under for double
underscore thunder future so dunder
future
includes is a directive that you can put
into your python code to say okay i'm
going to run this under python 2 but i
want it to behave like python 3 for this
specific kind of change
and so what we did at pinterest was we
went through these code modifiers code
transformers and kind of you know left
our system running on python 2
but incrementally made it more able to
run into python 3.
and it starts with these code modifiers
and the these kind of directives to the
python to compiler that says or python 2
machine that says behave more like
python 3 in this way right so kind of
incrementally including backwards
breaking changes from a future version
it's
kind of hard to explain but you'd have
to imagine
for a moment that essentially we're kind
of
choosing to to kind of gradually
cause that breaking change to occur a
lot of that was added by the way in
python
which kind of came out after the python
three so this was all added kind of
after the python 2 migration process
really started python 203 which was
years before pinterest relocation so
pinterest is one of the last companies
in part because of the size of the code
base to engage in this process
and so it starts with the code
transformers
you manually kind of incrementally
make it more able to run the python 3.
then we have the python future project
includes
some what's called future so it's just
instead of underscore underscore future
underscores for its future so from
future import so on and you can import
monkey patch functions so for example
you can import a version of the string
object creating function that creates
string objects that are more like python
3 than python 2.
once you produce python 2 code that
behaves more like python 3 and is
running out of python 2 and you can
start bringing in these future
functions or future classes that are
basically runtime shims that model the
behavior
of
python 3 under python 2. so you can
start
coding against the python 3 api
in your python 2 code base
by pulling in kind of new stuff into
python 2 from python 3. yeah so you can
migrate while you're also adding new
features to this existing code base
that's what you're saying right that's
right yeah you can migrate while using
features that would
typically not be available on prevent 2
or specifically the api that changes
under python 3 you can pull in more and
more of those changes
either through directives to the python
virtual machine or
through these kind of effectively user
space implementations of core python
objects that are consistent between
python 2 and python 3.
this is in contrast by the way to
another approach that you can use to do
the python 2 to python 3 migration
which is basically if statements you can
say if python 2 do this if python 3 do
that right and that kind of pushes the
complexity
into or makes the complexity in our code
base as opposed to kind of this module
that we're using library instead yeah
because if you have the complexity in
the code transformation tool at one
point hopefully you are done so then you
no longer need that complexity and then
you end up with a cleaner code base that
is 100 python 3.
that's right so when at the end of this
project the final stage when you're
actually taking this code that could run
under python 2 or python 3 by virtue of
this these directives to the
virtual machine as well as these kind of
user space versions of python 3 classes
and functions you can take that code run
it under python 2 right side by side
under python 3 confirm that they behave
the same
and then
you know
actually stop running under python 2 and
then remove
all those directives that are you know
the cleanup patch is a lot smaller right
it's just remove a few lines from the
top of each file that removes those
directives yeah so let's talk about
tools for this project so what did you
use to write transformations in or to
define the transformation to it was that
this jelly code tool that you were
talking about because that was a
javascript tool did you use that here or
did you use something else it's a yellow
code it is typescript it's javascript
based so it is not what we used here it
also i think came out a little bit later
so python future uses
the ast class that exists in the python
standard library so this is actually the
thing that python itself uses to parse
python
we use in python future as well and we
basically we take encode we
read it in use the ast module so it's
kind of reading code turn it into an ast
object which is an abstract syntax tree
and then we transform it we look for
specific so we would do like a typical
tree walk we look for for example maybe
look for a node that is a function call
type and once you've found a node that
is a function called type you want to
find out what function it's calling and
you can pass and say print right
so you can write a little piece of code
that says hey once you've gotten the
abstract syntax tree look for the node
that has a function called print and
then once we're in there then we can
change the asd in some way but if we
never find it then we don't do anything
so this is tooling then that sort of
depends on a certain programming
language
does this exist for any programming
language can you transform java with a
sim programming language
does this exist for any programming
language can you transform java with a
similar approach or is this a very
python thing to have built in
this is definitely a very paranoid thing
right most most compiled languages don't
have some you know version of this
most or maybe most is kind of a i'm not
sure if it's most but many interpretive
languages do so python pearl probably
have some version of you know an
abstract syntax tree class or some way
to model python code or pearl code or
php code for example in that language
itself but most of the time you won't
see that uh and in fact compilers you
may have to reach for kind of a compiler
tool change dig into there
so for example llvm is a kind of
compiler toolchain project that's out
there and has
what are called compiler front ends
which basically take in you know source
code as text and and produce what's
called an intermediate representation
which which is kind of code as data in
some way and you can use llvm front ends
often but in fact for some code
transformer transformers i'll use llvm
because ldm has amazing
uh coverage on the the front end side
and then so basically your front end is
take you know let's say c sharp code
turn it into llvm into intermediate
representation and then your back end is
just turn it back into c sharp code so
you can just write your own little you
know fake compiler that calls the llvm
you know hey
turn this c sharp code into intermediate
representation then
modify the intermediate representation
and turn it back into sushi
so what is the scenario that you would
want to do that where
you use this is this purely about using
like a compiled languages or are there
other differences between search tool
and the python tool
in this specific case of let's say an
llvm ir and an ast
i don't know off hand
what they might have in difference now
it is it is
i mentioned earlier you know there are
representations of code
as data that are not easily converted
back into source code because they don't
have
you know those white space or comments
or other parts that frankly aren't
meaningful to
the machine right if you're actually
turning it from source code to machine
code like if if your your tools that
you're using to build your code
transformer is really intended for code
compilers then you may not be in a good
situation but you can find versions of
this for almost every language that's
out there and it'll be very kind of tech
stack specific and so you'll have to do
your own research but those are some of
the ones that i've used
so of course we want to also know about
the pitfalls right what are some of the
things that you ran into one doing this
big migration what are some of the
mistakes that we should all make
i mean i think probably
there are lots of pitfalls i think
probably the the most immediate one that
comes to mind is you know not all two
use cases are gonna be the same
um so you have to remember that right
when you're reading documentation about
code transformation of some kind you
will find
instructions or guidance that is
generally true but may not be true for
your specific case
you know keep in mind that you know when
i was working with pinterest and we were
transforming a multi-million line code
base we found everything right we really
battled
we battle hardened the hell out of that
python future project and you know i
think that you have to be conscious of
that whenever you're working with code
transformer code out there is whatever
you're picking up chances are you know
it hasn't been applied in on on code
basis
as unique or as varied as kind of you
know the totality of all code in
existence and therefore you know your
how it applies to your specific code may
not be how it is intended to apply and
there are probably bugs in there too so
i guess you know as there are bugs with
any kind of software bugs that exists in
kind of cone transformation software can
be very
difficult to detect if you're not kind
of being intentional about it and can be
extremely difficult to debug
because it's basically like you know
code's removed your code's changing it's
just really hard
so talking about transforming
multi-million lines of code projects
what about performance what such a
transformation
did it take like an hour a day
well
in the case of of you know pinterest
right our migration took months probably
on the order of years frankly you have
to
think about
the project that you're embarking on
what you're trying to achieve and kind
of what your output what your desired
outcome is before you reach towards a
tool
and if you find yourself in a situation
where you know code transforming gets
you you know more confidence as it did
for us in pinterest way
more kind of you know less manual work
as it did for us pinterest then great
right so a multi-year project could was
cut down into something that was fewer
years right um but the running of those
tools is those manual code transformers
which is one part of that project and so
you have to kind of think about how your
project shape is going to be different
if you use this technique if you if you
are trying to make a change and you're
you're pulling in code transforming uh
as part of that change in automated way
so if you're incorporating code
transformation as part of your tool
chain for example that will as i
mentioned earlier code generators
increase your build time and so that can
become problematic as well so yes they
can take time to run it there is a
performance cost here and depending on
how you apply the technique or kind of
what you're trying to achieve you know
the trade-offs may not be there and they
may end up being yes it takes longer to
actually run the command and i'm
spending more time waiting but i'm
spending less time typing the same
things over and over and over again and
so that that is the the trade-off that
you have to think about and sometimes
that takes a
a view of the timeline a temporal window
that is bigger than just the build step
or just the actual part of running the
code itself the code transformer
yeah so i guess what you're saying is
that running the transformation itself
in such a big project is not really
where where the performance issues exist
because in such a big project it's just
maybe if it takes an hour it doesn't
matter if this is a project of a few
months
right and also like we we chunked it up
so like we ran you know 10 pieces of 10
files at a time for example out of
thousands of files and so each run on
each file may have taken a little bit of
time sure but that process of chunking
it up and and doing it in that way and
you know and having some automation
there
and netted out with something that was
much faster than if we had manually done
it right
so you already mentioned something about
making sure that the code was the same
because you can deploy it to a subset of
users and see if not too many errors
occur but that is like the code as the
running artifact but i was also curious
about sort of the code as an artifact
for reading did you also make any
improvements while transforming to maybe
some some stylistic issues did you also
try to improve the code base improve the
readability of the codebase or at least
not make the code readability worse
because the interesting difference
between transforming code and generating
code is maybe with code generation you
don't necessarily need to then maintain
the generated code but with this these
sort of transformation projects then
once you're done people will then
manually continue to work with the code
that you've transformed how to make sure
that this transform code is reasonable
for a person
yeah i mean i think i talked a bit about
earlier abstract syntax trees and
concrete syntax trees and how one major
difference is that they include white
space and comments right the parts of
the of the code source code that are not
relevant to perhaps the machine itself
that's running the code but rather to
the programmer who's reading it and so
if you have a code transformer that
eliminates those things that removes
them right then the output code that you
have is going to have those things
stripped out and that's going to become
less useful to the developer so
certainly that is you know something
that you have to be conscious about when
you're running a code transformer is you
don't want to eliminate or change too
much of the white space uh or comments
certainly if you don't have to
there also exists a set of tools out
there called you know auto formatters or
printers or something like that
sometimes called tiny petty tools or
think of it kind of like a linter so if
a linter does static analysis which is
basically you know to turn the source
code into data and inspect it somehow
and return you know a result this is bad
or this is a bad call or this is a
broken pattern or this looks good or
whatever right so that's a common
linting case a prettier will take a code
actually like add white space as needed
or comments
you know where appropriate break up
lines do whatever you know change
semicolons we're optional all the stuff
that are stylistic changes that
historically people would spend lots of
time arguing in comments on pull
requests over hey you know no semicolon
here but it's optional i don't care now
we have basically a tool that you can
run before you check in code that kind
of pretty auto-prints your code
so there's prettier in javascript land
black is a tool uh like this for python
i think it's you know you're gonna see
something like this in lots of different
languages where there's a sort of like
okay the open source community has said
here's the style that we want to more or
less standardize around because you know
every every little shop having their own
opinion and having a config file on
every repo you know for for the titan
script specific to my code base
doesn't actually improve readability
right in the sense that what really
makes a difference readability is that
everyone expects code to look like a
certain way and people can quickly look
at code okay i see this pattern of call
visually and so the cognitive process of
looking at a piece of text and
recognizing calls in a certain way is a
lot better when there are markers
present or spacing is as expected and so
it's really important certainly for
productivity not to eliminate that stuff
and i think if you have a code code
modifier that you produce and it removes
white space and comments it is broken
right because a8
is not really you know unless that's the
desired goal right in which case you
probably shouldn't be shipping that
little thing anyways because it's
probably a part of a bigger thing like a
compiler
so i guess what you're saying is that
you want to keep comments in place you
want to keep white space in place and in
some situations you might want to if you
are transforming anyway also run the
codes through a pretty fire tool so that
the output looks the same in similar
cases making it easier to read for
future developers
yeah and if you're doing a large
transformation project you'll probably
want to do that prettier run before
right because
an auto formatter it's supposed to be a
semantic noaa
right it's supposed to have no change to
the semantics of the code it just looks
different and so doing that first and
then running that big patch out the door
semantic no op you can make it change
easily then you create some sort of
tool chain ci cd kind of process that
auto produce code before it gets pushed
up then that will kind of minimize the
thrash to developers
nice that's really good advice
just speaking at my notes so this was
actually everything i wanted to talk
about is there anything we missed any
important tips or best practices or more
stories that you have to share about
code generation or transformation
i think that you know i talked a bit
about kind of the different techniques
for actually kind of getting code from
text into data
we talked about regex we talked about
kind of using text markers for an ast
and for folks who are interested in
learning more you know that that is a
great place to start start by playing
with with code you know take some script
that you've written see if you can turn
it into some sort of data object in one
way or another and try and manipulate
that and you can use tools that are out
there for your benefit but if you're
really you know if you're trying to
learn and grow what you know you know i
think it's it's great to build something
yourself even if the tooling is out
there already so i would definitely
encourage people get curious check it
out it doesn't take much to try and
practice this technique
and once you've kind of learned it
you'll find yourself with a new tool a
new power that you can use really a
super power that you can leverage to
make not just yourself more productive
but all the people you work with too and
that's a win-win
you know i think that's a great closure
of the episode knowing how to parse and
transform code it is like a superpower
oh yes definitely
so any places where we can read more
about you like your blog your twitter
any links we should add to the show
notes
absolutely i have a website uh
jmabler.gov
and you can also find me on twitter
their handle is jordan
and you can learn more about the python
future project which sends you know
links in the show notes as well python
future
yeah
we will make sure that those are all in
show notes
great okay
thanks for being on the show today
thank you so much
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening